All right. Once you are done with the clients work and mark the deliverable is complete,
حسنًا، بعد الانتهاء من العمل وتسليمه إلى العميل،
it is time for you to get paid for it.
حان الوقت لتلقي المقابل المادي.
If you're going through a freelancing platform this is much easier,
إن كنت تعمل على منصة للعمل الحر، فسيكون الأمر سهلًا،
since usually these platforms have an escrow feature where
حيث تطلب هذه المنصات من العميل
the client deposits the payment for the project before the project starts,
إيداع المقابل المادي للمشروع قبل بدء العمل عليه،
and the platform releases it to
وتقوم المنصة بإعطاء المقابل المادي
the freelancer once both parties agree that the work has been completed.
للموظف الحر بمجرد اتفاق طرفي المشروع على انتهاء المهمة.
The advantage of this arrangement is that the money lies with an intermediary now,
ومن مميزات هذه الطريقة وجود المال لدى وسيط،
and could be helpful in dispute management that a third party needs to be involved.
ويمكن أن يكون هذا مفيدًا في إدارة المنازعات التي تحتاج مشاركة طرف ثالث.
For example, if the platform agrees that the freelancer indeed deserves for payment,
فعلى سبيل المثال، إذا أقرت منصة العمل على أن الموظف الحر يستحق حقًا المقابل المادي،
they could release it to the freelancer since they have
فيمكنها إعطاء المبلغ إليه، بما أن المنصة لديها المبلغ بالفعل،
the money even if the client is not willing to make the payment for the work done.
حتى وإن لم يوافق العميل على الدفع مقابل العمل الذي قام به الموظف الحر.
This also helps in timely payments since the freelancer is no longer
ويساعد ذلك أيضًا على تسديد المبالغ في الوقت المناسب نظرًا لأن الأمر لم يعُد
dependent on the client to make the payment. A [inaudible].
خاضع للعميل ليقوم بالسداد المادي. [inaudible].
You really don't want to get into a situation where the platform intervenes.
ليس الهدف هنا أن يصل الأمر إلى تدخل المنصة لحل الخلافات.
As much as possible,
فيجب تجنب الخلاف قدر الإمكان
try to see if you can settle it with the client yourself. All right.
حاول تسوية الأمر مع العميل بنفسك.
When it's time to get paid and you are on a freelancing platform,
عندما يحين الوقت لتتلقى أجرك وأنت على منصة للعمل الحر،
you could just mark the job is done on the platform,
يمكنك وضع إشارة تفيد أنه تم الانتهاء من المهمة،
and you're all set for the escrow to be released and get paid.
وفي انتظار تحرير ميزة الضمان لتتلقى الأجر.
If the freelancing platform does not have
إن لم يكن لدى المنصة
an escrow feature or if you're not working through freelancing platform,
ميزة الضمان أو إن كنت لا تعمل عن طريق منصة للعمل الحر،
you can just send a note to the client to get paid.
تستطيع إرسال رسالة للعميل تطلب أجرك.
Now at this point,
الآن، في هذه المرحلة
some times clients may insist on
بعض العملاء يصرون على
a formal invoice to be sent to them for the services provided.
طلب فاتورة رسمية موضح بها الخدمة التي قمت بها.
That usually depends on how the internal processes work in the client's company,
ويتوقف ذلك عادة على أسلوب الإدارة الداخلية في شركة العميل،
usually the auto-generated note or invoice sent
وعادة ما تكون المذكرة أو الفاتورة الآلية التي تقوم
by the freelancing platform maybe enough or the client.
المنصة بإرسالها تلقائيًا للعميل كافية.
But the client may need a formal invoice directly from
ولكن قد يحتاج العميل إلى فاتورة رسمية من
you as a freelancer who provided the services.
الموظف الحر مباشرة ليوضح فيها الخدمات التي قام بها.
You are anyways need to do that for off platform clients.
أنت على أي حال بحاجة للقيام بذلك للعملاء من خارج المنصة.
In the next section, we'll cover what goes in,
في القسم التالي، سنتطرَّق لأمر
in such an invoice for the client.
فواتير العملاء.